[Music]
hello hello we are live good evening
good day everyone welcome to a new
episode of ask a budget
i am excited to be back amongst you all
it's good to see your smiling faces
wherever you are
um
okay let me take a look at who all is
there and let me quickly greet some of
you as if i can
[Music]
good evening good day everybody it is
great to be back with you all
so as i
i'm sure you know today i'm gonna take
questions that you have asked in the
comments in the previous week or so
and at the end of that hopefully if i
have some time i will take some live
questions if that is possible
so let's begin with question number one
okay ishwar roshan says india's total
kovid cases per 1 million population is
30k
while the u.s and europe have more than
200 k code cases per 1 million
population same goes for debts 360 per
million in india while 2 000 plus
per million in the u.s europe
india while having a much larger
population than these individual
countries has recorded much less scored
cases and deaths
should we see this as an accomplishment
or is it like we are conducting less
tests and debts are going unregistered
as claimed by the so-called experts by
seeing such a large population of india
okay i'm not sure about the figures but
i get the gist of what you're saying
the overall case load in india is much
much lower than in the west in europe in
the us and overall debts per million
also whatever the figures are are much
lower in india than in these countries
so the question is is this just under
reporting is india under reporting the
cases and the deaths that's what the
western journalist new york times
washington post have been saying for the
past two years india is under reporting
blah blah blah blah blah
well you know what if india was under
reporting the cases and there were many
more then the hospitals would be
overflowing there would be a crisis
everywhere and you would see it
and it's not happening
it's not happening so it tells you that
india has managed this pandemic
way better than the west
in the west they have these triple
vaccinations and boosted doses and four
times vaccinations israel is the most
vaccinated country in the world
it's it's technically part of the west
and you can see the case load there you
can see the number of cases per million
the number of deaths per million it is
incredible
so there's clearly something that india
is doing better than the west what would
that be
well first of all we have a different
vaccine
we have an indian vaccine that we are
using we are not using the rna-based
vaccine and the western vaccines
the indian pharmaco pharmaceutical
industry is not
well the entire business model is
different from that of the west
so in the west it's all about making
money out of people out of the pandemic
that's the that's just the way it is in
india it's not that so the indian
vaccine is the best vaccine in the world
it has the fewest side effects the
fewest number of vaccine injuries or
whatever you call it and it is the most
effective two doses you are done whether
it's o micron or whether it is sigma or
delta or gamma or
psi or whatever it is
it works
and secondly um
the way the vaccine or the pandemic has
been managed in states like up etc there
is this entire kit they give to every
person who is infected and it really
works really well and so on so india has
done an excellent and exceptionally good
job
at managing the pandemic india is not
may trying to monetize the pandemic the
way it is the west is doing especially
the united states where everything is
monetized even a tragedy is monetized
every person has a certain monetary
value for the vaccine companies and so
on so that's not the case in india
so india is so what is the the
impression that certain
uh western publications have been trying
to create and certain
motivated journalists on twitter etc
they keep on going about it that india
is under reporting cases that's bs
it's complete nonsense by now they've
been thoroughly exposed they will still
keep on doing it but no one's listening
to them anymore nobody is listening to
them anymore
these uh
big journalists and big publications
have lost their credibility over the
past two years completely lost their
credibility
initially they were trying to push a
certain narrative that you know they
were saying this is a natural pandemic
there is no lab leak and that has been
totally discredited now so don't believe
what these people are saying india has
done
extraordinary well
in managing the pandemic
next question please pick my question
why are there no revolutionary movements
against china in tibet
or illegally occupied parts of mongolia
and turkmenistan
now let's let's talk about tibet
so in tibet there have been
these insurrections there have been uh
from time to time these uh uprisings
against chinese occupation and they have
always been crushed brutally
so i think there was one in the 2000 in
the early 2000s or in the first decade
of the first million or second
millennium
third millennium
in the first decade of the 2000s i think
there was one large
uprising
and in the 20th century
after the occupation of of tibet there
were several uprisings they have all
been crushed brutally by the chinese
occupying
army so these have been brutal brutal
put downs of these insurrections and
there have been many of these the thing
is that we don't have all the reporters
and journalists and tv cameras and all
that in chinese occupied tibet or any
part of china so we don't know what's
happening in there and they try their
best to suppress all the information
they try their best from preventing news
from leaking out of china so we don't
know what's happening there are there is
a lot of resistance against chinese rule
but it is all crushed very brutally
what's happening is that tibet is is
essentially
garrison province it's full of chinese
soldiers
and the communist party has pushed in
lots of han settlers chinese settlers so
what's happened is that the entire
demography of tibet has been
restructured
re-engineered the native tibetans the
indigenous people are now a minority in
their own country
and there are more chinese than tibetans
in tibet so that's what's happening so
they are they have tried all kinds of
means
to suppress the tibetans and prevent any
kind of uprising uprisings still happen
and there are all kinds of protests
there are lots of self-immolations and
all kinds of terrible things happening
there
but the news never comes out and the
western media is not interested in tibet
the west has essentially given up tibet
to china they are only interested in the
fate of the uyghur people in xinjiang
etc because of various other reasons
they don't care about tibet so lots of
things are happening in tibet lots of
things have been happening but slowly
slowly the movement is being crushed and
stifled uh when it comes to other
other uh territories that have been
occupied by the by the chinese like
xinjiang you there are all kinds of uh
there's all kinds of resistance
happening but the news doesn't come out
so there is violent resistance it's not
like satyagraha they're doing they're
not doing any satyagraha non-violent
protest they are
they are
opposing
the chinese occupation through violent
means but
and the chinese call it terrorism
and so on so sometimes the news does
leak out filter out but most of the
chinese try to keep a very tight lid on
all the
on whatever is happening in there so we
don't get to know about it the west is
interested in xinjiang
the west they don't care about the
people of tibet so it's double standards
it's it's that's just the way the west
is
hypocrisy
uh monarchy says can you please explain
the petroglyphs of ratnagiri how old are
they let's take a look
let's take a look right so let me share
my screen
let me share my screen okay let's take a
look at the petroglyphs of ratnagiri
so if you look at the images
the petroglyphs of ratnagiri are these
uh images these carvings that have been
uh etched into stone
in the ratnagiri region of the
of southern india which is part of
maharashtra
so as you can see there are these
ancient carvings this is the
large carving of an elephant
uh
this
this is a human figure
this is a wild it's a bore
this seems to be a bovine animal
this i'm not quite sure maybe an insect
or something not quite sure and you can
see there are
quite
complex figures here this is a spiral or
a labyrinth of some kind
this
could be a rabbit perhaps
and there are other such things as well
you can see there are multiple animals
human beings etc that are represented
and
this is most likely a deer not a
kangaroo we don't have kangaroos in
india
and a human figure and so on so forth so
this is what the petroglyphs of
ratnagiri is
these are very ancient
carvings
in rock in the ratnagiri region of
southern india maharashtra essentially
how old are they
i believe that these carvings are
believed to be about 12 000 years old or
so
now the thing is that it is very
difficult to accurately estimate the
date of a rock carving
so when it comes to
when it comes to
organic material let's say you have a
skeleton of an ancient human being
you have bits of bone you have teeth you
have hair
or you have something that's made out of
wood
etc then you can easily
date that organic material
uh via
carbon dating carbon 14 14 dating and
there are other ways also updating that
organic material but when it comes to
rock
rock is typically millions of years old
and and a carving doesn't have any
doesn't typically have any organic
material in it unless they have put some
kind of there they have
inserted some kind of paint or something
which may have some organic components
in that case it's easier to date it but
typically rock carvings are almost
impossible to date you can only estimate
a rough
estimate or guesstimate
roughly what the age could be like so i
believe they have used a variety of
ways of reasoning and
the archaeologists have estimated this
uh these these rock carvings these
petroglyphs to be around 12 000 years
old
so they represent an ancient more
ancient phase of indian civilization and
culture
and that's what it is so
these have been discovered i believe
reasonably recently
so a lot of research can be done into it
and
and see what is the connection with
later day
cultures
with i mean is there a cultural
continuity what exactly does it
represent does it represent worship of
animals or just
i mean nobody takes the time and the
trouble to do all kinds of
detailed rock carvings it takes it's a
lot of effort right
so you would not do it unless it had a
certain
special significance
so what is the significance what does it
represent in the
religious and cultural context and what
is the relevance of that
when it comes to cultural continuity
that these things need to be looked into
so i hope the asi or whoever else
is looking into it will do this research
and maybe one hopes to see some findings
coming up in the coming days months
years so that's what i can say in brief
about the
ratnagiri rock carvings
okay chi-ching says are the britishers
of then and today's generation proud of
themselves that they could capture and
rule so many countries in the past you
know that um that sort of attitude that
sort of pride is always going to be
there even if you look at the people of
greece they are still proud of their guy
alexander the warlord right
they are very proud of him and the the
things they did and they they try to
bask in the reflected glory of that
now there is this uh
belief among people that you know we are
a great people or whatever the thing is
this
if you look at any any ethnicity any
culture there's only a few people at any
given time who are truly great maybe one
percent or maybe less than one percent
maybe one percent of one percent that
sort of uh
percentage
of the population exhibits true
greatness but when that happens
everybody tries to claim that greatness
from themselves and they try to
democratize that greatness
that's not really how it works
of course some people like indians they
have produced more intelligent and great
people
than others percentage-wise and so on so
that's how it is so the british they
have claimed this greatness for
themselves what they have done is
conquered the world brutalized the world
pillaged the world destroyed the world
destroyed the ecology of the world
destroyed ecosystems destroyed cultures
it is nothing to be proud of
yeah sure you were able to to weaponize
science and technology and destroy
cultures that were more peaceful than
you
and you were trying you were able to
superimpose your culture your language
your religion
on various conquered peoples do you
think is it it is greatness
that's the thing right i mean look at
what they've done in africa if you look
at the length and the breadth of africa
the paths that were occupied
and destroyed by the british you will
see that they have eradicated the
beautiful african culture from all these
places
you will see most of these people
africans trying to speak broken english
and they are all they have all lost
their traditional culture and religion
today
it's all been wiped out and replaced by
whatever came from europe
and you will see that happening in other
parts of the world also where the
british have had their influence
including parts of india
i don't see this as a sign of greatness
i see this as a sign of barbarity and
depravity
but yes
there is a certain amount of pride that
the british still have they might not
exhibit all that exhibit that all the
time because nowadays you know you have
to be
politically
correct and all that
and so on but yes it is there and you
will see that especially among the older
folks that we ruled the world we
civilized the world we created the
commonwealth and we gave you culture and
we gave you
laws and we gave you buildings and all
that nonsense
so yes
the british still have
at least an undercurrent of that pride
they may not exhibit it
openly but it's there but you know
what's happening now
all that
the pride will remain as long as they
are reasonably prosperous
the uk is very prosperous the per capita
gdp is very high standards of living are
really really excellent compared to
other parts of the world because of all
the loot and plunder which they did over
a few centuries so all of the wealth was
considered was relocated to england and
that's why they are they are enjoying
the fruits of the plunder even today
whether they realize it or not but now
what's happening is that the the
countries they destroyed especially
india and to some extent china as well
which they tried to destroy so these
countries are rising again now in the
next 50 years the per capita gdp of
india is going to rise
most likely above that of the uk china
is already
rising very fast so in the next 50 to
100 years they're gonna be
from a gdp uh perspective from a living
standards perspective most likely gonna
be inferior to the east and it is at
that point that all that pride will have
disappeared because your pride typically
depends on your level of prosperity
if you have destroyed other countries
you're more prosperous then you feel
that you're superior but if you did
destroy them in the past and now you
have gone down compared to them then all
that pride will not exist anymore so
that's just how it is typically a
person's level of
uh
pride
and arrogance depends on how much money
they have that you will see in nations
and you will see in individuals also
that's just the way the world works so
that's that's what you have so yes the
yes what teaching asks is very uh
relevant
they still have
a great deal of pride in what they have
done in destroying the world it won't
last long
okay push pandra singh says what led to
the decline of the sikh kingdom after
the demise of maharaja ranjit singh
and can you please explain the
significance and achievements of
maharaja ranjit singh so let's begin
with the second half the significance
and achievements of maharaja ranjit
singh so
we have to understand
what sort of world maharaja rajit singh
came into
uh it was
before
the advent of maharaja singh the
northern part of india and most of india
by the time was kind of
occupied
and
was in the process of being destroyed by
the turks right
and in northern india in punjab kashmir
etc you had the abdali destruction
the secondary chicken thing and all that
so
this region was also brutalized it had
been brutalized by the afghans by the
persians and by the turks afghans the
pashtuns mainly and the turks of course
so that's the kind of world that uh
maharaja ranjit singh was born into
right and india was not there was no
political unity in india
there was
there was a lack of
sufficient
resistance to the foreign occupation so
that's the world he came into he created
this kingdom they call it the sick
empire i call it the sick kingdom
because it was not that large
but what he did was he kicked out the
pashtuns from kashmir he freed kashmir
and
and punjab of course he unified
politically everything under his domain
and he
he launched these punitive expeditions
against the pashtuns against the afghans
he kicked them out of kashmir he
he freed kashmir he also conquered parts
of pashtun territory
and he put that under his rule
and he undid all of the brutality that
the
foreigners had perpetrated he banned cow
slaughter
and things like that you know so it was
a very good period very uh a period in
which
there was
justice and peace
and indian culture was was again honored
so that's what he achieved military
accomplishments and
peaceful rule and a sort of uh revival
of culture for some time and that that's
what he achieved maharaja ranjit singh
now if i am not mistaken he passed away
in
1839 listen when i give a date it's it
could be wrong okay i'm not very
don't take my dates literally just look
it up if you want the details i will
give you a rough
um approximation of when things happened
so i think he i he most probably died in
and what happened after that is that
within 10 years the sikh kingdom sick
empire
disintegrated within 10 years and why is
that it's because there was no stability
political stability after his demise
after he died his son came to power his
son lasted a year or so before he was
assassinated murdered then his son came
to power he also could not last more
than a year
and i think within the next 10 years
after between 19 between 1839
and
1849 there were at least five or six
rulers
in in uh who succeeded maharaja singh
and none of them was capable of of
consolidating the power and
and ruling the kingdom effectively none
of them was good enough to do that and
that's the simple reason why the sikh
empire disintegrated in the
anglo-sick wars the british prevailed
and they took over the
sikh territory and the amount of
territory that maharaja ranjit singh had
conquered from the pashtuns it fell into
british hands it eventually became the
the boundary dividing boundary
eventually became known as the durand
line it is currently
the boundary the the border between
pakistan and afghanistan
and that is the root of the border
dispute between these two countries
so that is
what um
was able to achieve
and
unfortunately because he did not have
a successor with the same kind of
strength of character strength of will
and the ability the political and
military ability to hold everything
together he lacked that
none of his descendants was able to do
that and that's that's why the the
kingdom disintegrated within a decade
so that's just how it happens it's all
about succession you need the right
successor
you may be a great king great emperor
but if your successors are not
worthy
of being able to rule a kingdom or
empire like the the kind of kingdom that
you have then your
legacy will be very quickly flittered
away by them and that's unfortunately
what happened
okay we have a couple of questions
bunched into one armaan says thank you
for this interesting video i'm not sure
which one but yeah you're welcome sir as
an iranian i'm very curious about the
origin of our race and religion from the
perspective of hindus because personally
i believe the most realistic and
near-to-truth story comes from the east
instead of the west it would be great if
you could reveal more about iranian and
indian relations
let's take that question first the
second one is also interesting but let's
take this one first
so listen
we need to look at history from an
evidence-based perspective what the west
tells us is that there was an aryan
invasion from north from europe and the
aryans split into two branches the
iranian branch and the indian branch and
we are all related indians and iranians
we are audience but we came from outside
we are outsiders we are actually our
ancestors very wide-skinned european
people and today we have different
shades of brown because of various
reasons so indians and iranians are like
sister civilizations and we are
descendants of ancient
aryan invaders that is what most people
believe in india and in persia today but
look at look at our texts so look let's
take a look at the in the oldest uh
uh the the
foundational uh the founding myth or
story
literary history of of of persia of iran
so the text that is the most
authoritative is the the
is the shanama of
which was written roughly roughly
approximately a thousand years before
today give or take a century or so don't
uh look it up if you want the exact
accurate date so the shadow of fair dos
it was written about a thousand years
ago before today
and it recounts the entire history of
the persian people
right
now if you look at the origins the
origin story in the shaarama it is
exactly the same as the origin story in
the rigveda
it is a mythological story it says that
the in the beginning we had the great
sun god
in sanskrit we call the great sun god
swar
swara means the sun it also means gold
okay
so
means shining so when in sanskrit you
say
it means the shining sun
in the shahnamaz in in philadelphia
it is
what does korsad mean
in ancient persian in the old persian
language sir became ha
so swarakshetta became
which slowly became corsaid
so the founder of persia
the oldest oldest person that is uh
mentioned in
in the shahnama is worksheet or corset
now in the vedic
tradition the sun
s-o-n son
of swarks was yamakshet so yama was
the first human being yam yamaraja right
yama
yamakshit because he was the son of the
son so he was also shining so he was
also
in the shade
so the story is exactly the same then
you have the great hero treita
who is called tretun in chanana so you
can see the ancient oldest origin story
is exactly the same in persia and in in
the in the shana and in the rigveda and
so on in the vedic text in the vedic
tradition
so it is clear that the origin of the
persians and the indians
is the same now was there an rna vision
but that's a whole different topic i
have gone into detail in that there are
lots of videos on my channel
what the evidence what the hard
scientific evidence archaeological
evidence genetic evidence all of that
what it tells us is that there was no
iron invasion from europe into india or
persia
at some point in time there was a battle
in ancient india in the western region
of india
region east of persia there was a big
battle the battle of ten kings
and
the losers the the the clans the vedic
clans that lost were forced into exile
out of india westwards
one of them most likely was the parshwa
clan
of indians rig vedic indians sanskrit
speak speaking people they went
westwards
and they settled in a land west of india
they were called the parshwa people the
ones who held the parshu the battle ax
and they gave their name to the land so
the parshwa people gave their name to
the land which became known as persia
their capital was parshvapur persepolis
so that is the true origin of the
persian people
it is well it is not part of mainstream
history
but that in fact is the truth like you
said all the west the the eurocentric
perspective is all about
it's all about misrepresenting and
distorting history we have to rediscover
our own history from our recorded
literature from the archaeological
scientific evidence and all that so that
is the relationship between india and
iran we we used to be the same people
now this event must have happened many
thousands of years before today it is a
vedic event it is it's a
it's probably a puranic event
so maybe it happened a few thousand
years ago
and as we know the language of ancient
persia it was used to be very
similar
to sanskrit old persian it was just it
was it was
i would say that it was the old persian
and sanskrit were closer than spanish
and portuguese are
are today right so it was a matter of
pronunciation like
like british english and american
english that sort of thing right
and eventually persia developed its own
uh traditions its own culture and it's
obviously a separate civilization in its
own right it used to be today it is
something else
that's a different story so that in
brief is what i would say and you can
certainly look up the ancient literature
don't look at english translations
western translations look at the
original shanama i think persians can
read the original sharnama which is
written in the portion of a thousand
years ago but it's quite similar to
today's persian language so read that
and try and look at what the vedic texts
say you will see a lot
of commonality and that tells you that
the indian persian people used to be the
same long ago
right the second question is by follower
of ahura mazda or mazda are ancient
persian dynasties like like uh pishda
dhyan and kayanyan dynasties mentioned
in the rigveda all persons believe that
we have a common ancestor called kyomars
or kumar who was the first ruler of the
pistadiyan dynasty
um no
these ancient persian dynasties are not
mentioned in the rigveda or any vedic or
puranic texts what we know is that there
was this battle in the parsha clan
went westwards after that there is no
mention of the parshwa people the
parshwa clan who were rigvedic indians
so clearly these are dynasties the the
pista is the first uh they call it a
mythical dynasty right what nonsense
they must have obviously existed so the
president dynasty is supposed to be the
first dynasty of ancient persia that's
what
um
what is recounted orally in oral
histories and literature et cetera and
the second one is the kayanyan dynasty
which came after the
dynasty the kyanian dynasty is supposed
to be named after the great kavi kings
so you know what kavi means in persian
and in sanskrit it means poet poet kings
so that's how it is but uh
there is no mention of these two
dynasties in the rigveda or any vedic or
puranic text which indicates that these
dynasties emerged after the persian
people the parshwa people went west of
india that's what most likely happened
it happened these dynasties emerged
after the powerful people reached what
is now known as persia or iran
so
that's what i can offer you my friends
but very interesting questions and great
to
have these questions
okay rohit says i see our culture and
language is more similar to kurds than
turks but in the history it says turks
invaded india
so were the turks and kurds the same
back then good question right so who are
the kurdish people the kurdish people
are considered to be an offshoot and
outgrowth of the iranian people the
persian people
right now i just went into detail about
how the persians and indians are related
culturally ethnically genetically all
that same origin right
and therefore if the kurds are an
offshoot of the persians then clearly
their ancestors were also
in the vedic times indians
and that's why you will see
that the language is an indo-iranian
language
the kurdish language it is it is
classified under iranian today
but iranian comes under indo-iranian
right it's part of the broader
indo-iranian language family so the
kurdish language is part of the
indo-iranian language family genetically
if you look at the genetics i have not
i've not seen studies or anything but
if genetic analysis tests are done you
will see similarities between the kurds
persians and indians no doubt about that
so
that is the reason why even the culture
even the culture will have common
commonalities the kurds are now all
muslims i'm i'm
sure most of them majority i'm sure but
if you peel back the layers of culture
you will see some remnant of pre-islamic
history among the kurds like the navroz
festival
which is in spring i believe which will
be coming up soon
and so on so you will see layers of
pre-islamic culture which will have
their
ancient roots
in the vedic culture so that's why
you will find that indian language
indian culture etc is way more similar
to the kurds then to the turks now you
say that turks invaded india well that's
a later invasion it happened about a
thousand years ago
right so the turks have nothing to do
with the kurds the kurds
their relationship with india goes back
thousands of years
right the turks had nothing to do with
india they they are a completely
different ethnicity and culture they
invaded india about a thousand years ago
thousand twelve hundred that it's it's
roughly around that time
so
that's how it is so there is no
commonality similarity between the turks
and the kurds
and the reason for the similarity of
culture and language all that is because
of way more ancient history common
history which dates back to the vedic
times so that's the answer
anmol says what should be the
appropriate tax rate for a country shri
rajiv dikshitji used to quote the arthur
shasta ideas lectures
and advocated for a minimal tax rate of
five percent as it is said lower the tax
higher the recovery even china would
term a state extorting
massive tax as beggar state
curious to know your views on revenue
mobilization and taxation all right
okay so i'm not aware of what shri rajiv
ji has said or not said i'm not aware of
that so uh what i will say is this
uh from what i recall
in the arthashastra chapter 5 section 5
i'm not sure which part of the book it
is but uh
it says that
i think
there's a whole lot of
it goes into a great amount of detail
about taxation different tax rates for
different activities different
professions and so on but i think
overall it advocates one sixth
the tax rate i think it believes it says
should be about one-sixth of what
the
earnings are
so if the value of goods is
x then the tax should be x divided by
six that is the overall
uh what i recall what is uh stated in
the arthashaster that seems to be the
optimal tax rate so one six works out to
about or 16 or so so that seems to be
the optimal tax rate as per the
arthashastra of sheri
uh i would say that the state does need
tax of course the tax should tax burden
should not be
extremely high otherwise it's going to
ruin the country
now the thing is my views about revenue
mobilization taxation i think we need to
simplify taxation as far as possible
we already have something called the
gst
you go and buy a toothpaste a toothbrush
you're paying tax because there is a gdp
which is included in the price of your
toothpaste or toothbrush
you go and buy a kilo of potatoes
there's going to be gdp on that also
and other taxes local taxes whether you
like them or not it's there so let's
talk about the gdp any single product
good service you buy
and whatever price you pay for it
gdp is included in that so you are
already being taxed for everything
that you purchase every tax every i mean
every every good every service that you
purchase there's gdp included in that
then why do you need additional taxation
why do you need income tax after that
why don't you make it as simple as
possible
tax everybody via gst
what did i say gdp earlier um
i apologize if i did gst i mean gst
so if everybody is already paying gst
for everything they purchase in the
country why do you why do they need to
be taxed additionally additional income
tax additional road tax additional god
knows what are the tax
just make it simple
one gst for the whole country and of
course you can have different things in
your categories in gst as per what the
government and the politicians decide
so what i would say is that
make
let there be just one tax in the country
keep it simple as simple as possible
keep it transparent just one text make
it make
include everything in the gst
don't make people run around in loops
and in circles
filing tax returns and income tax and
whatever else
make it simple that's that's my view
simplicity is the best thing for the
country
so the tax has to be there the state the
the the government
needs the tax the tax revenue to the run
the country to invest in infrastructure
to to give services to the country all
that is required of course you need tax
for that
so of course they should tax the
citizens
it should be a reasonable amount of tax
i don't know if 16 is enough today
maybe you can tax 20 even up to 25 i
think is easy
is acceptable for most people i suppose
more than 25
is is just too much i would say
so there needs to be tax 100
everybody should pay tax 100 everybody
is paying tax whatever they buy because
you have gst so why put why tax
an income that has already been taxed
right why why do you have multiple
layers of tax
so what my views are that tax sessions
would be simple and straightforward and
transparent
rishi says
is it possible for a moon to have its
own moon
so what you're essentially asking is it
possible for a satellite to have its own
satellite now look at the solar system
you have the sun in the middle and all
the planets go around in elliptical
orbits for simplicity call them circular
orbits
so you have the earth going around the
sun so this the earth is a satellite of
the sun yes
now the earth has its own satellite
which is called the moon
and if you look at the moon you have
certain spacecraft that orbit the moon
for instance chandrayaan-1 and
chandrayaan-2
you also have a several nasa satellites
that orbit the moon so these can be
regarded as moons
of the moon
and so the answer is very simple a moon
can have its own moon and even that moon
can have another moon of its own very
simple
it's just a simple basic newtonian
mechanics so yes to uncertain brief a
moon can certainly have its own moon yes
okay sudeshna biswas says my question
may be silly no it's never silly ask
your questions please don't ever feel
your questions are silly so do you think
that as a scientist one can one could
instantly remember all the laws of
physics and not forget certain things my
teachers my teacher told me that since
you were to become an engineer so
remember all the laws of physics
properly but does that mean that at any
random instance scientists can recall
all the laws of physics properly
my question is do scientists ever forget
a few laws of physics well you see it's
like this
when we talk about the laws of physics
we're not talking about text
three paragraphs of this law and seven
paragraphs of paragraphs of that law
of a law of physics a law of nature is
expressed in in the form of a
mathematical equation
all the laws of physics are
expressed
in the in the in the form of
mathematical equations now when you are
learning physics the the process of
learning physics takes years all right
and to become a good physicist
you have to internalize all the basic
principles
of nature of physics all these basic
laws of physics and how do you
internalize them you
solve problems how do you learn math
problem solving you solve lots of
problems whether it is
arithmetic whether it is trigonometry
whether it's algebra whether it's a in a
differential calculus integral
calculation calculus differential
equations whatever it is
you can only learn mathematics by
solving lots and lots and lots of
problems similarly do you learn physics
by solving lots of problems so
how do you solve the problems in physics
you apply the laws of physics the
equations so when you solve dozens
hundreds of problems and you spend
hundreds of hours solving these problems
it simply becomes part of your internal
makeup
out of the operating system that you
have
so that's what happens so uh the basic
the main principles and the laws of
physics they become completely totally
internalized you can recall them at any
time but you cannot recall hundreds of
equations and all the derivations at any
given point in time now when you are
studying to pass an exam
whether it is the iit-jee
or what is it gate or whatever for being
an engineer or whether you're studying
for the physics gre or whatever
for that you have to memorize and cram
all kinds of equations into your head
and once you're done with the exam you
let it go and you forget it all it
doesn't matter
so for a working physicist there are
certain laws of physics certain
equations that they will be able to
recall instantaneously the other stuff
you can just open a book and look it up
what really matters for a physicist is
that you know how to solve problems and
do research
so that is a different kind of skill
altogether
that is
i suppose some people are born with that
aptitude some people have to develop it
but to do a good to be a really good
physicist you need to know how to solve
problems knowing the laws of physics so
some laws of physics the core
fundamental laws of physics you can
never forget
and if you're a good physicist you will
not be able to forget even if even if
you want to but everything else you can
just look it up open your textbook open
your reference book look up and use that
so that's how it works so essentially
you don't have to memorize every goddamn
thing it's just not humanly possible but
you must have a good familiarity so once
you look something up you should know ah
yes i know what i did with this i know
what this equation is i know how to use
it
that's how it goes
all right a curious wanderer says can
you please explain how the cheddar man
is having features like dark brown skin
and blue eyes thank you okay let me uh
explain what cheddar man is
let me share my screen
with you
cheddar man cheddar man
where is it
here it is so this here gentleman is
called the cheddar man
this is an individual an ancient human
being who lived in
the british islands in present-day
england
about 9 000 years before today if i am
not mistaken about 9000 years before
today
and what they had
is
his skeleton his body right
and his skull which looked like this and
today we
have the technique of forensic facial
reconstruction as you can see here's a
different individual they were able to
rebuild his face and so on so this is
the face of
the guy called cheddar man
and on the basis of his skeletal
structure this is the structure of his
skull they were able to reconstruct his
face this is what he looked like and
because we now are able to
do genetic analysis etc we know
that this individual had most likely had
dark brown skin
and blue eyes
and the question is if this person lived
in
england
present-day england why did he have dark
brown skin and why did he have blue eyes
which is a perfectly good legitimate
valid question excellent question
so it's like this the genetics
your genetics determine what skin color
hair color eye color you have and it is
different genes
that regulate your skin color your eye
color and your hair color
so if somebody has let's say light skin
it is not necessary that they will also
have blue eyes and blonde hair you will
see people with white skin with dark
eyes brown eyes and dark hair
you can see lots of examples of that
so uh
the genetic mutation that is responsible
for light skin fair skin what we call
european fair skin white skin whatever
you want to call it it originated about
seven eight nine thousand years ago in
india or maybe in the middle east and if
you listen to my to the conversation i
had with dr nirajara and in the podcast
which is available on this channel you
will see that
the middle east is also part of the
indian subcontinent population wise it
used to be historically part of the
indian subcontinent so the genetics
there were also the same as the genetics
in india right
so
the genetic mutation for fair skin which
you find in ireland europe etc that
originated
in ancient india
and it indicates that there was an
exodus of migration from india to the
west
and that's why
most of europe today has various degrees
various shades of light or fair skin
now
this population influx into europe that
caused all these changes came from the
east they call it the yamnia invasion of
europe very violent invasion and once
again if you listen to dr niraj the
yamnaya where 99
most likely of indian origin r1b is
their petroleum haplogroup which is of
indian origin
and they replaced ancient european
populations violently they essentially
massacred all the men right
so before these light-skinned people
came into europe you had darker skinned
people in europe
that's what you had
and this individual this gentleman
uh cheddar man is a very good example of
that
so there you have it the ancient
europeans looked like this whether it is
the cheddar man whether it is it is the
kromanian man let me show you the
in commando
let's see what he looked like
so they uh represent him like this in
various skin colors
but typically he was a brown skinned
person
there are more accurate representations
more recent ones
i'm not sure if i have it here but the
even the chroma know man was a brown
skinned person he also most likely had
blue eyes
okay so let's not go into that right now
so the point is
that the genetic mutation for light skin
entered europe from the east from india
with the yamnaya invasion that happened
about 5000 years ago roughly about 5000
years ago it started before that even
the people who lived in europe ancient
europe they had brown skin now the
genetic mutation for blue eyes is a
different
is a different set of genes the genetic
uh code for blonde hair or red hair is
also a different uh genetic mutation so
that's not always correlated and
therefore you had the these set of
characteristics that were prevalent in
europe before the yamna invasion and
replacement of the people of europe so
it's all about genetics
so that's how
ancient europeans had dark skin and most
likely blue eyes
and you will see that even in india you
will find blue eyes even with with
people who have darker skin or whatever
you blue eyes or green eyes or whatever
it's quite rare in india
maybe one percent of the people may have
it one or two percent but you do find it
and you also do find people with blonde
brown hair or blondish hair even red
hair
in western india northern india and
maybe other parts of india also it's
quite rare but it is there so all these
genetic mixes components are prevalent
to various degrees in india too
okay kostub says what was the common
language for communication between two
linguistic between two between two
different linguistic groups before
english took over the position
uh before the english became the
predominant uh
ethnic group
or or the or the conquering people in
the world
before the rise of english you had
french as the diplomatic language in the
west
so even today in diplomacy for the
knowledge of french is is quite
common quite prevalent diplomats
typically speak french
good diplomats are supposed to be good
at fringe and all that so before english
you had french
when we come to india when you come to
india today as you can see i am having
to speak in english if i don't speak
english
maybe half of my
audience may not understand me very well
especially in the southern of india
that's just the way it is today because
of colonization
so before
english was forcibly shoved down the
throats of the indian people
it was sanskrit
that was the common language of
communication across
the
civilized indian world which included
southeast asia indonesia
of the philippines and so on so forth
you know eastern asia vietnam and all
even the chinese when the chinese
travelers like shwanzang etc they came
to india
during the tang dynasty for instance
what language do you think do you think
they spoke in india i mean uh someone
like schwanzong i believe in also they
entered india through gandhara which is
presently afghanistan so when they
reached gandalf
the which valley was it
the bamiyan valley they said oh finally
we are in india now right so that was
ancient india at the time
and then they passed through gandhar
into punjab kashmir through kashmir
punjab then they went eastwards and the
eventual destination was nalanda which
is in present-day bihar magadha
so all of these parts of india obviously
at that time also they would have had
different languages that were spoken
locally regionally
and yet these chinese travelers were
able to converse with everybody speak
with everybody communicate with
everybody and find their way all the way
to
bihar to magadha
so obviously there was a common language
that they were able to speak
that was sanskrit
so in india before the destruction of
our culture by foreigners sanskrit was
the civilizational language
if you go to if you went to southeast
asia if you want to present the sumatra
or java you could speak to the locals in
sanskrit at least the officials and the
kings etc
government people administrative people
they would all understand sanskrit
sanskrit was the high language of
civilization it even today
is considered to be the prestige
language in indonesia people still have
sanskrit names
even though the people of indonesia are
muslims today
so the common language of communication
throughout the
indian subcontinent and the indianized
world was
sanskrit
right
and as we know it was first the people
of kalinga who indianized southeast asia
eastern asia and then it was the the
cholas
under raja rajendra most likely yeah
who further indianized
southeast asia
and it was always sanskrit now some
people will say you are wrong abhijit
there are so many tamil speaking people
in malaysia and so on that is a much
later influx
it happened during the british
occupation of india and southeast asia
it was indians who were forcibly taken
there to work as laborers and whose
descendants lived there today
and most of most of them were from
southern india from tamil nadu because
tamil nadu is on the east as we know and
that's that was closer
relatively to southeast asia so people
from tamil nadu were taken as
indentured laborers or whatever and they
were forcibly settled there so that's
why you have tamil speaking populations
there
but during the chula conquest it was
sanskrit that was the language
so uh so that's the answer it was
sanskrit
and here we go uh
there's always a few questions about
this so let's go vishal says in most of
the countries outside of south south
asia which you mean by which you mean
the indian subcontinent the hindu
communities over there recognize both
sanskrit and tamil as sacred languages
and speak the speak their mother tongue
along with the language of that
particular country so why this tamil
versus sanskrit debate is still going on
in india
both our ancient languages both have a
rich literary
musical tradition for ages why can't the
people stop chauvinism and get along
with their both official languages and
there's a second question similar to
this
by peace out as a half kashmiri half
tamil person raised in switzerland i am
fluent in kashmiri german french hindi
and tamil
thus kind of understand the link between
the languages of india and the west the
oldest known literature in tamil
tor la kapiem written by a brahmana
person lol
talks nothing of the river saraswati or
the davidian aryan races but instead
mentions various rituals and brahminical
or what are known as hindu customs then
how is it that the dravidian parties
were and are able to successfully
brainwash the population down south they
are that there are different race of
people
so these are both very good questions
uh the oldest tamil literature the
oldest evidence of the tamil language
comes from the the the
from the sangam era which
uh is around 300 or 400 bc around 300 bc
that's the oldest known
uh textual literary evidence of tamil
and in the sangam literature
you will find the references to the
vedas to the rishis you will find
references to the himalayas and the
lands north of the himalayas
which totally
refutes and falsifies the claim that the
tamilian tamil speaking people were
confined to the south of india even in
300 bc there are references to the lands
north of the himalayas in sangam
literature there are references to vedic
texts and vedic customs and vedic
rituals traditions rishis all that so it
it totally goes against the myths that
have been created that the tamil people
are a separate people are separate
ethnicity separate race right and there
is something called a davidian race
there is no reference to dravidians and
aryans in any sangam literature they
have taken one word and tried to mangle
it and make it sound like dravidian
dravidian or something which which is
what they do cherry picking of data
uh so
so it is very clear that these are see
tamil is 2 300 years old at least and if
the literature exists to existed
in 300 bc it means the language must
have existed long before that
so one can safely say that tamil or
proto-tamil would have existed at least
around 1000 bc so it's at least
3000 years old and the older versions of
the language may have been way way older
than that nobody can dispute that so i
am not saying this language is older
that language is older but from the
evidence we have hard evidence
clearly sanskrit is way older than that
i don't want to create unnecessary
controversies going saying this is
bigger that is because we are all the
same people come on
we are the same people now the thing is
why is it that the dravidian parties
have been able to successfully brainwash
the population firstly all tamils don't
believe this
right all tamil people do not believe
this nonsense but i but the majority i
it looks like do believe that the tamils
have been oppressed by the aryans and
there is a dravidian race that has been
oppressed for five thousand years or
three thousand years or whatever
the dating is
and that it is a separate
ethnicity separate culture separate
religion the tamil culture was a secular
culture there was no brahminism or
whatever they call it it's all nonsense
so why is it that this notion has taken
has gained so much currency it's because
the education system in india teaches
you lies first of all it teaches you
that there is something called an aryan
invasion
and that the north indian people are
descendants of white aryans south
indians are defending descendants of the
real people of india
so it creates this invader and oppressed
dichotomy
and once you create that sort of feeling
it becomes an emotional thing and you
know you you you feel an emotional
connection to the story
so these lies are being taught in the
education system and secondly the
education system doesn't teach students
how to think for themselves
it doesn't
uh
doesn't uh teach students the art and
science of critical thinking how to know
what is the truth and how to know what
is lies
how to
discern
lies and falsehoods from the truth
it doesn't teach the art of discernments
discernment it doesn't teach the science
of critical thinking
and therefore it it only tells you that
you have to unquestioningly swallow
whatever your teachers
and your superiors tell you whoever is
in a position of power
whoever is in a position of authority
whatever they tell you you have to
unquestioningly believe it so for 20
years for 15 16 years that they use the
teacher as the
person in power the positive authority
once you become
an adult once you're no longer in school
college university whatever then you
start looking at the people in the media
as the ones in authority
and therefore you have to
unquestioningly believe whatever they
tell you and that's why the politicians
who own the media
i'm not saying the entire media is owned
okay let's not make that claim
but the majority of the media as we all
know
is biased
it has agendas
it is controlled by various the majority
not all
has funding funds etc from various
sources and if you look if you follow
the money you will know where it comes
from
and therefore all
of it has a certain agenda a certain
political flavor certain ideological
flavor and that's why the media is also
biased most of it and that's why you
will find the same old lies being
perpetuated by media the the tamil are
separate people
different ethnicity different race
they have a separate culture the killer
d thing
proves the iron invasion happened and
the killer d uh civilization proves
there was a separate tamil culture what
nonsense man have you seen the evidence
there
have you seen the data have you seen
what they found how does it show that
there is a separate tamil culture
killer d is one
archaeological site it is not a separate
civilization so all of this narrative is
created
to make the people believe that all of
this is true
and the people because of the
indoctrination that they have gone
through
during the 15 20 years they spend in the
education system they just blindly
believe it i don't blame that for it i
don't blame it then for it but that's
just how it is and and the dravidian
parties the south indian parties mostly
in tamil nadu mainly in tamil nadu
they have created this tamil
versus aryan dravidian versus aryan
uh
dichotomy they are playing off it they
are creating this sense of oppression
and
that's how politics works create a sense
of oppression alienation and then and
then position yourself as a savior
so that's what's going on and because of
political considerations this all of
this has gained a lot of currency so you
will find this belief prevalent in many
many people especially in tamil nadu not
all not all thankfully but many people
unfortunately
that's
why it is so we are the same people
please understand this if if tamil
people are watching i'm sure they are
watching and they will watch in the
future
please understand this we are all the
same people not south east west the same
people the same civilization the same
culture
our ancestors
they are the same beliefs the same
culture the same civilization we all
are the same people
so
genetically also we're the same people
it's it's proven
all right
siddhant says question related to
geopolitics
i read a theory of a multi-polar world
order where there are multiple
superpowers coexisting and hopefully
finding an equilibrium of some sort
do you think this type of scenario is
possible if yes will it be stable for a
long time if no then this means will
there be another cold war when india
tries to become
a superpower as it happened during us
versus ussr
and now u.s versus china or can india
handle it well diplomatically
okay so uh
is there going to be a multi-polar world
or a bipolar world
we are already going towards a bipolar
world multi-polarity is nonsense it's
not going to happen
power is never shared
it's always one superpower or at the
most two superpowers there is no space
on this planet for three superpowers
it's very hard for that for such a
scenario to emerge if it emerges it will
only be a transient scenario so we are
already seeing
a bifurcation of the global systems we
are already seeing
the emergence of of the of the new cold
war we are already inside we are already
in
the cold war 2.0
so the world is now
bifurcating into a bipolar system the
western uh system the existing system
which which was dominated by the united
states
uh and a different pool which is the
dragon bear what velina chakrava calls
the dragon bear which is the systemic
cooperation between china and russia
so that's the kind of bipolarity we are
already seeing
and
so we are inside
we are already in the middle of a cold
war
when india tries to become a superpower
well that's not going to happen anytime
soon maybe in the next 20 30 years we
may be in a position to
uh achieve that
so can india handle such a thing
diplomatically you know power is not
diplomacy diplomacy is one of the
elements of power but hard power comes
from something else altogether it's
economic power military power
to be a superpower you have to position
yourself you have to place yourself in a
position to be able to intervene
militarily
anywhere in the world within a 30 to 60
minute time frame
that is the hallmark of a jio of office
superpower
and secondly you need to be in control
of the world's reserve currency today
the world's reserve currency is the u.s
dollar
so these things only the u.s can do the
chinese can't do therefore the chinese
are not a superpower people are talking
about china as a superpower it's not a
superpower it's an aspiring superpower
it's a local hegemonic power it's
bullying all its neighbors but it's not
not yet a superpower india is not even a
proper local power okay let's look at it
very coolly from a realistic perspective
india cannot get even get its neighbors
to behave
and therefore india is not even a proper
local
hegemonic power
you know what happens right the sri
lankans kill our fishermen
maldives you they kick out an indian
company we know what the pakistanis do
anyway we know what the attitude of
bangladesh is towards india from time to
time you know how nepal is going into
the chinese camp so india is not even
able to
control its immediate neighborhood so
what superpower it's not even a local
power regional power right now
but maybe india is
uh abiding by the maximum of then
shopping
which says bide your time and hide your
capabilities and work very hard so maybe
that is the phase india is going through
um
so yeah so we are
seeing the emergence of a new bipolarity
a new bipolar world order
and we are already in the middle of a
new cold war
okay swastikas says if russia starts a
war on ukraine what will be its effects
on india and whose side india should
choose
there could be a war possibly there are
rumors being spread right now by various
reporters journalists that the russians
are planning to invade ukraine next week
or so
so for future reference today is the
12th of february 2022 february 12 2022.
today is a saturday so next week
apparently russia is planning to invade
ukraine let's see how it goes whether
the prediction is correct
so if russia starts a war with ukraine
what will be the effects of india not
much not much it's a regional war it's a
regional conflict it will be localized
in eastern europe
and uh
so unless the chinese take that as an
opportunity to also invade taiwan
simultaneously it's not going to have
much of an effect on india so if it's a
simple russian invasion of ukraine it's
going to be a local thing there's going
to be repercussions globally the the u.s
will intervene in some manner nato will
get involved and there could be a bigger
conflagration possibly maybe not let's
see
for india there will not be much of an
effect or whose child whose side india
should choose
india should always choose one side only
there is a side of india
this is not india's fight
then why should india get involved india
should remain neutral in this
india should pursue its own long-term
national interest
now how does it
augment perform or further india's
national interest by getting involved in
a conflict
in which india has
has no nothing to do
so india should remain neutral in this
and india should just work
assiduously
in furthering its long-term national
interest by building its economy
and its military its internal systems
its infrastructure and all of that so
that's what india should do
aishwarya says um thank you ashwarya so
the question is i wanted to ask what
would have happened
if the british would not have invaded
india
if the british had not invaded india
then we would be speaking marathi
because see what the british did was
they destroyed the maratha empire
and
replaced the marathas as the hegemonic
power in india
the marathas what they had achieved was
that they had
step by step slowly decade after decade
eroded
the turkic occupation of india the
turkic power in various parts of india
and by the middle of the 18th century
they had
re-established
indian home rule or what they called
hinduism
all across india across most of india
and their territory their their
dominion extended to the southern parts
of afghanistan afghanistan and so they
so parts of gandhara were part of the
territory so they had destroyed
the turkic military machine
and they had reduced the so-called
mughal emperor to nothing more than that
mayor of delhi
right that's what the marathas had done
through conquest through military power
and what the british did was that they
dis they defeated the marathas and it is
all thanks to the infighting among the
maratha peshwas
to the petty politics and infighting
among the marathas that's why the
british were able to take advantage of
that
and slowly take control of india
so had the british not invaded india and
not defeated the marathas then india
would be speaking either marathi or
sanskrit today
we would of course have local languages
but the
state language the language of the state
administration all that would have been
most likely marathi or sanskrit maybe
both to some extent
so that's what would have happened had
the british not invaded india and you
would not have all this
religious strife and all that and all of
that which the british engineered in
india you would not have all the
dravidian aryan nonsense
and all of that all of the division that
you are seeing in indian society today
you would not have that
so that's what i can offer to you in
brief
um
next question
bhanu pratap says in the battle of the
ten kings the bharatas finally won the
battle and the kuru empire was
established wanted to know whether this
is the reason our land was named bharat
and secondly does this somehow lead to
the western world to conclude that the
eastwood movement of aryans in the aryan
invasion theory
uh right
so yes it was the the bharat clan the
bharata clan that won the battle
and it established the guru by a kuru
and that is indeed why our land our
civilization is called bharat
so the bharat clan its progenitor or one
of their ancestors was was king bharat
right
so that's why
that's why india
is known as bharat historically right
and that
battle has nothing to do with the
alleged easter eastward aryan invasion
or whatever if you look at the uh
at the outcome of the battle you find
the migration and the flight
escape of the defeated plants westwards
so they're actually all the events they
actually go they fly in the face of the
fake aryan invasion myth so the aryan
invasion theory has nothing to do with
the battle of the ten kings the battle
of the ten kings if you look at the
events it actually completely disproves
the iron invasion
myth
but you are right the la the reason our
land was named bharat is
is because
it was the bharata clan that
won the bharat clan which won the battle
and established what became the kuru
kingdom or the kuru empire in
in india
okay aditi says in all our temples and
other architecture both men and women
alike are portrayed as bare chested yes
correct why is it so when is it true
that traditionally covering up was not a
sign of modesty this feature
is seen in extended india also in
cambodia where apsara dancers and
carvings don't cover up
if covering up was in way is inherited
in india
due to foreign invasions why is it seen
in countries east of us
and so
and there is this opinion floating
around in southern india the priestly
and warrior class used to cover up and
did not allow the so-called lower caste
women to cover their upper body so as to
humiliate them please enlighten them all
right all right all right all right so
you are right aditi that uh if you look
at any ancient carving in temples and
other architecture you will find that
men and women both are bare chested
there is no controversy in that it's a
matter of fact go anywhere and see it
you will find it
so why is it so you asking it's because
of india's climate india's climate is
hot and humid right anywhere especially
in southern india
and it doesn't make any sense in that's
that sort of climate to to cover your
body extensively there's no need for
that and there was nothing in india's
culture that said that
being bare chested was any is was bad or
or
immodest in any way whatsoever
men women both used to be bare chested
and that was the way it was you can see
ancient black and word pictures of taken
during the british times in various
parts of india in which men and women
were bare chested
right
especially in the south because in the
north you had the turkic invasions
because of which the women had to were
forced to cover up because the turks
used to
treat women as pieces of meat
unfortunately
so if you look at the p of if you look
at the culture of india before the
turkic invasions men women were both
typically bare chested and it was not
considered to be a sign of immodesty or
any such thing
it was not considered to be the sign of
being uncivil a sign of being
uncivilized uncultured any of that
and the same existed like you said in
cambodia where absolute dances used to
be bare chested yes but why do they
cover up today because of the influence
of western culture worldwide if you see
old black and white images pictures
of upside dancers in cambodia you will
find they were bare chested
and there was nothing shameful about
that it is the
it is the
influx
of western culture and western
moral norms worldwide that has made the
entire world cover up
in eastern asia you women and men used
to be all bare chested you will find
lots of photographic evidence of that
even if you look at japan there used to
be i remember uh
these
female divers fisher women who used to
dive underwater and all that they used
to wear very scanty clothing they used
to be bare chested and there was nothing
shameful or dishonorable about that but
today everybody covers up it's because
of the the
the
hegemony of western culture and moral
values and normative behavior that this
has happened
okay so so that's why it has happened it
has
it was never part of eastern culture
that you have to cover up and where and
all that
uh then the other opinion is that the
priestly and warrior class used to cover
up in south india but did not allow
so-called lower caste women to cover up
to humiliate them it is lies it is lies
it has been debunked you can see
articles online which debunk that there
is this myth of this woman called
nangeli and all that
that may be something unrelated or
something
tangentially related but these are all
colonial lies that have been created to
cause this this divide in indian society
aryan versus davidian low casters high
caste all this nonsense
these are all colonial myths and
fabrications the origin of all these
lies
is in the colonial era after the british
took over and they did all kinds of
various
uh
social engineering
experiments to try and break up indian
society and it's worked you can see
there are so many divisions in this
indian society today
so why don't you take a look at my
the conversation i had with uh
dr meenakshi jain in which she has
spoken about how the british engineered
she has not gone into this particular
matter but
she has spoken about the methodology
they employed to
further colonize india and to anglicize
and christianize india and to do that
you have to first show the local culture
the indian culture as primitive as
backwards and and and inferior
and once you create these divisions in
society you put one group against
another you create artificial divisions
artificial groups in society artificial
strata in society
and then you put one against another
then it becomes easier to induce people
to convert to their foreign religion and
so on
so that was all part of the
are part of the colonial agenda and it's
really worked and unfortunately even
today the colonial agenda is at work
through our education system and our
political
class
the media and all that so we are getting
we are sliding further back
and we are getting more and more
colonized even 70 years after the
british officially departed from india
that's just
unfortunate something needs to be done
about this
okay mayor says is there politics in
science stream also if yes how is that
if no is it good or bad
you know
the one central characteristic of
human society
is that
there's politics what is politics you
form coalitions groups of like-minded
people of people who have similar
interests and you work together because
in numbers you have more power
and therefore you find the
formation
of various factions in society you will
see that happening within a single
family extended family you will see that
happening in inside a city in the state
in a country and so on so forth
and you will see that in various
professions
if you work in any office in any let's
say private company or whatever you have
office politics petty low-level office
politics you will face that
and even in the scientific
establishments even in academic systems
you have the same politics the same
faction hearing and all that and you
also see that certain uh
certain um
certain theories gray gain more credence
certain theories gain more
more currency in science for instance in
science you have the
even today you have the aryan invasion
theory that many
so-called scientists linguists
geneticists are still trying to push
it's it's dying out but it's still
among the older ones you still see those
attitudes right so there is that is
politics that's agenda driven uh
behavior
and you will also see it in physics so
for all these years for the past 30 40
years there's the there's been the
theoretical physics has been under the
stranglehold
of what some people call the string
theory mafia
so all of the funding in north america
especially even today in all the physics
departments goes into
string theory research even though
string theory is more or less a failed
theory by now
it has not made any even a single
testable prediction
it gives rise to 10 raised to 500
possible versions of the universe the
so-called string theory landscape
it's utter nonsense
i mean a theory needs to produce some
results that you can test it's not
succeeded at all and yet you have if you
look at the
online literature it's all string theory
string theory string theory
so
that's a consequence of politics so yes
you have politics in in science as well
typically politics is bad
politics leads to
group think
and it it prevents people from thinking
outside of the box i mean you can
express certain opinions and explore
certain theories but you will be
marginalized if you do if you do that
you may try and publish papers but your
papers will not be accepted they will be
rejected and therefore you will
you will no longer be in the mainstream
of research so that is all political so
a politics is always bad it it hinders
research it hinders original thinking
politics makes forces people to conform
to certain behaviors into certain
streams of thought
right so politics is bad but
unfortunately it exists in science as
well
okay wisdom bro says why uh have we
consistently kept falling into the hands
of enemies for the last thousand years
is there any loophole in our culture and
upbringing we don't understand there is
no loophole in our culture my dear
friends there's no loophole in the
culture
this is not about culture
it's about power it's about political
power it's about political unity
if you have political unity in the
indian subcontinent nobody can dare to
try and invade you they're gonna be
smashed destroyed look at the times when
india was politically united
the mauryan era
the kushan iranda the great kanishka
kanesha the great
the gupta era
the the the era of
the peda the chola era
and the marathi also when briefly india
was united at the time nobody could
defeat india
so the past 1000 years we were invaded
when we were not politically united
where we had all these small kingdoms
fighting each other for supremacy
and that's why india fell to the to the
invaders it's not because of any
cultural loophole
it has nothing to do with culture it is
simply that
there was a lack of political unity and
stability that is what caused what
happened
what i call the the millennium of
humiliation
herschel says having read so much
history have you concluded in your mind
that there was possibly the one and only
sarathan dharma on the planet and
everything else is just different
adaptations and manifestation of it
what i have seen in my study of history
is that
throughout most of history
the world
every
significant culture was polytheistic
i would not say it was all different
manifestations of dharma i would not say
that i would not make that claim
but yes the world was polytheistic
whether you look at the
polynesian cultures
whether you look at the various african
civilizations
but then you look whether you look at
the hunnic peoples the turkic peoples
and the mongolian peoples there they
were all polytheistic
if you look at india obviously we had so
indian culture if you look at the
ancient persians even as zoroastrians
they were polytheistic
many people especially zoroastrians will
try and say no you are lying
zoroastrianism is a monotheistic
religion
nonsense
zoroastrianism is a polytheistic
religion don't lie
and then obviously in europe also across
eurasia you had various
forms of the ancient indo-european
culture which you could
which you could consider to be
uh various variations of the ancient
vedic culture so in eurasia
from india all the way westwards to
ireland in iceland you had various
manifestations of the same culture which
you can
possibly
consider to be various local
manifestations of sanatana dharma
you could possibly consider that to be
corrupted versions of sanatana dharma
possibly so in eurasia yes india and
west of india
but you also had cultures in
let's say the americas north america
south america i would not
i'm not quite sure if there was any
connection with india there may be but
we still haven't found
undeniable
incontrovertible evidence of that there
seems to be circumstantial evidence that
there was something but
as of today i cannot from the
perspective of hard evidence i cannot
make the claim
so the world was 100
polytheistic before the emergence of the
abrahamic religions even the arabs were
polytheistic
even the babylonians were polytheistic
right
the
the acadians the horyans all of them the
egyptians all of them were polytheistic
so the world was polytheistic before the
emergence of the abrahamic religions
so that's what i can tell you i would
not venture to make the claim that the
whole world was
i would not make the claim
ayaan says did ancient people know about
the dinosaurs there is an interesting
carving in the angkor wat temple
resembling the stegosaurus
what's your opinion there are even
mentions of elephants with four tusks
and sea monsters like viritra listen
how many animals
do you want to talk about let's talk
about the dinosaurs
uh
did ancient indians know about dinosaurs
i don't know i haven't seen any
hard evidence
of the knowledge of the existence of the
dinosaurs in india
see the dinosaurs exist died out about
65 66
million years before today that is about
6.7 crore years before today
homo sapiens
our species
has existed
for about
two and a half lakh years
250 000 years
a quarter of a million years all right
so there is no overlap between the
existence of the dinosaurs
and human beings none whatsoever
of course dinosaurs still exist but
don't tell anybody that's a different
story that
okay so um the dinosaurs in that large
monstrous form tyrannosaurus stegosaurus
diplodocus brontosaurus apatosaurus
iguanodon all of those dinosaurs that i
doubt about 66 million years before
today and i have never seen any temple
carving or anything that resembles a
dinosaur from my own lived experience i
have not seen that if there is any such
thing let me know in the comments below
and i'll take a look at it
now you see that there is a carving in
angkor wat resembling the stegosaurus
that's interesting i haven't seen it but
i will try and find it
so that's an interesting thing you tell
me
i also
i think it's also believed that the
chinese had this uh
this tradition
of billy of this belief in dragons right
the dragons once existed these mythical
creatures
maybe they had found maybe they may have
found some
skeletal remains fossilized remains of
dinosaurs and maybe they construed that
as the existence of dragons long ago so
that is a possibility
that's a possibility
right so that's what i can tell you as
far as i know
i have not seen evidence of indians
having carvings of dinosaurs and all
that
sea monsters like vrithra that's a whole
different story
the vritra is a serpent it's a great
mythological serpent that tries to
swallow the ocean and indra the great
warrior
has to defeat britra with his great
vajra which is the thunderbolt
and the vajra is also the hammer the
hammer so so indra is a hammer god and a
thunder god it's the same as zeus
in greek mythology zeus also defeats a
great sea monster great sea serpent
typhon
t-y-p-h-o-n typhon is that great snake
that zeus defeats jupiter
zeus peter became jupiter
was the roman god who did the same thing
and the nordic equivalent of indra is
thor who is also a hammer god and a
thunder god and he defeats a great snake
called your mug and your mugandra you
want to take a look at him
the great yormu gandhi let me show you
that's what the great nordic snake looks
like your
the snake that thor defeated
so that's the same pattern that you see
mythologically in all these
indo-european cultures which all
originate in
ancient vedic india
but from the perspective of dinosaurs i
have never seen any carvings of
dinosaurs personally if you know of any
let me know in the comments below
all right uh mayur says
tell your set of principles for learning
geopolitics and suggest any book which
helps in understanding geopolitics
geopolitics
i i don't think there is any course
in any university that deals with
geopolitics
i have personally not read a single book
on the topic or subject of geopolitics
like this is a textbook of geopolitics
or an introduction to geopolitics there
is no such book you to understand
geopolitics you have to understand a
vast variety of things first of all you
have to understand world history not
just your local history but the victory
of the entire world
so it takes a lot of time to to
to learn to study that to read that to
internalize that
without understanding history you will
never ever understand geopolitics and
we're talking about world history here
not just your local country's history or
whatever so the first prerequisite to
understanding geopolitics is
understanding world history
the second thing
is you have to understand the cause and
effect
relationship
in historical events
just understanding or studying history
will not teach you anything you have to
understand cause and effect how do
things happen and why do things happen
there's always a cause and effect
relationship it's not always obvious
but it's there so you have to understand
that that's a deeper level of
understanding of history thirdly you
have to understand power what is power
power is the big mysterious thing right
what is power
there are different levels of power
different kinds of power
right
you don't understand why empires rise
and fall there is again causality the
cause and effect change the chain then
you have to understand global systems
modern global systems the financial
system the system of supply chains you
have to understand all of that you
understand economics
at the macro level at least
you understand
military history you understand how the
militaries of the world work
you understand
the difference between
policy and doctrine and strategy and
tactics and execution
so that these are some of the things
that you need to understand
in order to gain an understanding of
geopolitics
so i don't know when i realized that i
understand geopolitics at least to some
extent
but i have been studying all these
things i've been fascinated with these
things for
forever
and
that's why
at some point in time i realized that i
actually understand geopolitics i
understand how things work and all that
so it takes time
i would say it would take at least 10
years of study
at least 10 years of study minimum
at least to become a novice a beginner
in geopolitics you have to dedicate to
study for five years all of these things
so there is no book
there is no book available for
understanding geopolitics unfortunately
i have not come across any
i have only studied books in books about
history
books about military strategy book about
books about various empires books about
uh supply chains and economic systems
and all that and
various
wars world war one world war two uh the
punic wars and many other things and
slowly slowly slowly you you
the you make the internal connections in
your mind after reading a lot
so that is how i
have acquired an understanding of
geopolitics i don't know if how other
people do it
there are courses
on geopolitics
from a systems perspective i think of
one of my previous guests velena
chakarova if you look at her website she
has a course that she offers
or you could perhaps if you want enroll
for the course and and gain an
understanding from from that perspective
she
studies uh and analyzes geopolitics from
us from a systems perspective like the
economic system the supply chains the
infrastructure the various institutions
like the un and their interrelationships
the diplomatic
world and all that
right so there are various ways of
studying and analyzing geopolitics so
it's it's quite complicated it's not
easy
but it's something that's worthwhile
doing if you are interested in all of
these different things
so all of that is geopolitics
um gunpot says how can we and the indian
government deal with foreign involvement
in the internal affairs of india through
religious organizations and ngos
see foreign interference in a country's
internal affairs is possible when the
foreign interfering power is much more
powerful than the country they are
interfering with
so they essentially compel the country
to accept this interference or else
there will be consequences
right now
there are certain countries
there is a certain country there is way
way way more powerful than india i am
not talking about china
you know marx karl marx
spoke about the
invisible hand
that
mediates and influences and controls
global events
so we don't we don't know who this
invisible hand is but we know that he
speaks english
so there are certain powers in the world
that are way more powerful than india if
they want they can destroy india
and
they
essentially compel
india to accept certain kinds of
interference
otherwise there will be consequences for
india
right now india is not strong enough to
resist that what should india do
keep quiet
keep a low profile
abide your time and work hard to develop
yourself into a stronger nation
india
well see india's gdp right now is around
3 trillion or so right
approximately
india needs to reach the 10 trillion
dollar level in gdp
once india reaches that stage
india is going to be a different kind of
beast
it will be whole different kind of power
economic power and with economic power
there comes a prof proportional level of
military power
that will be a different india
when china was in india's position
3 trillion gdp china is to behave in a
very meek
manner
they did not have this full four-year
diplomacy and issuing threats for
everybody they had a very conciliatory
approach they used to keep quiet and
they would be routinely humiliated by
the western nations and they used to
just swallow their pride
and accept it and they knew that they
were
building their country
and in the future they'll be able to
push back
so that is exactly what india needs to
do right now india needs to develop on
the
india needs to focus
and work very hard on the unglamorous
stuff
building infrastructure building
highways building railways
building the industries developing the
industries building up the
infrastructure
increasing india's gdp india needs to
reach 10 trillion dollars of gdp and
then it will be a different story so
that's what india needs to do
what india needs is every year at least
10 percent 10 gdp growth anyhow we need
to achieve that
and that's the government's job
we have one job
uh build india up develop the economy
make the economy grow as fast as is
humanly possible
and that needs to happen for at least 10
to 20 years
then we will talk
all right
divya says
can you talk about power what it is and
how do we understand power etc
okay power
has any of you seen the movie
fight club
so if you have seen the movie you will
know the rules of fight club
the first rule of fight club
is that you do not speak about flight a
fight club
and the second rule of fight club
is that you do not speak about fight
club
and so on
so the same goes with power
you do not speak with power there are
secrets to power that you do not reveal
but this
but that is not what i do right
i'm here to share information share
knowledge i don't keep secrets
so let me reveal a couple of secrets
about power
so
let me give you two rules
two rules to understand
power
so if you are a king
or if you are a dictator
or if you are a president or prime
minister
to be in power and to remain in power
you need the support of other powerful
people
that is
undeniable
you can never be in power without the
support of other powerful people
now why would other powerful people
support you because they get something
in exchange
they gain something from keeping you in
power
maybe they they get the gain is that you
allow them to stay alive or maybe you
give them some benefit you know they
gain some money some some power of their
own which derive which is derived from
your power so the first rule of power
is that these people who are essential
to your staying in power you have to
keep that group of people as small as
possible
keep the group of people
who are
essential to your staying in power keep
it as small as possible that is the
first secret of power
the second secret of power is that
keep the number of people the group of
people who you can trust as large as
possible
so essentially the people who you can
trust are the people who are loyal to
you
and the people who will obey your orders
your government machinery your officers
your officials etc
you keep that group as large as possible
so you don't minimize one group and
maximize the other group
okay you can start with understanding
this
and then maybe in the future we'll talk
more
so these are two secrets of power that
nobody will tell you
okay
let us take one more question
karthik says can you please speak about
napoleon bonaparte's life
some people say he was abducted by
aliens and scientists claim that they
have found a chip in his skull
okay
listen guys this is between you and me
okay do not tell this to anyone
this secret must not leave this space
you see napoleon was not abducted by
aliens
he was an alien
but don't tell anyone
all
right okay let's take some of you let's
take a few questions from the
from the live chat you have any
questions i'll i'll take two three
questions
um
yeah i think everyone is uh
okay let's take this jeet says if
egyptian civilization was great then how
how did it go extinct everything has ups
and downs every empire every
civilization is ups and downs look at
the romans they are so great where are
they today
look at the greeks they were so great
where are they today
look at the babylonians are syrians they
have a great great empire great
civilization what happened
it went extinct
and so on and so forth everything has
ups and downs
the egyptian civilization was an empire
imperial form of governance etc and they
went extinct because they were first of
all defeated by the romans
you had the hellenic phase of egyptian
civilization when uh
things like tolemy etc greek origin
kings were ruling them then you had the
roman conquest during julius caesar's
time
when
you had the hegemony of the romans
and
and then you had the arab
islamic conquest of egypt which was the
final lady in the coffin and that's why
it disappeared that's why it went
extinct so today if you look at the
people of egypt they will obviously have
the ancient
egyptian ethnicity but culturally they
are arabs they speak arabic in their
religion as you know as the
religion that is prevalent in the
arabian
part of the world
so that's how it
went extinct
other questions
do we have other questions
is india going towards glory or is
declining now i would say
india seems to be going in the right
direction it there there needs to be a
lot more work
but i am cautiously optimistic
let's not talk about glory yet
glory is in the future hopefully
right now india needs to go towards
a state of
reasonable prosperity we need to reach
there first i think we are going in that
direction so i am
cautiously optimistic glory we will talk
about later but we i don't think india
is declining now in certain ways
culturally civilizationally india is
declining
if things continue like this in the next
50 to 100 years there will be no more
indian culture left hindu culture
hinduism so that is something that needs
to be addressed
maybe it will be addressed
when the time is right
um
how to improve one's personality
be yourself
and learn
learn and become confident how do you
become confident first of all you can
there are two ways of becoming confident
if you are financially prosperous you
are confident secondly if you are
physically healthy and strong you're
confident so work hard
in your career
acquire
money
and secondly
stay healthy remain healthy and become
the best version physical version of
what you can be and thirdly acquire
knowledge
interact with interesting people all of
that will make you a well-rounded human
being and then be confident about
yourself and be yourself that's how you
improve your personality it doesn't take
it will not happen overnight it will not
happen next week or next month but it is
something you can consider to be a five
year or ten year project because life is
long
right
so that's how you improve your
personality in a nutshell
all right
um
okay the harappan people used to worship
animals they used to worship bulls
instead of cows how do you know that
how do you know that
there are no carvings of brig vedic gods
in mahindra how can we say that harapans
were not the same as we're the same as
the vedic so okay have you seen the
great carving of pashupathi
the the
the great
person who is sitting cross-legged with
animals all around him
and you will see later representations
of the god shiva in the same form
now shiva is a vedic god he is mentioned
in the vedas
and therefore you have
a representation of shiva vedic god in
in mohandara in the so-called harappan
region you will find shivlings there
lots of shiverings
so what does the shiveling indicate
the worship of a vedic god
a god who is mentioned in the vedas
you say they worship bulls how do you
know the worship bull sir
there are carvings and sculptures of
bulls it doesn't mean it was for worship
maybe it was
some other purpose we don't know right
we cannot assume it was worship
there are also carvings of tigers
and lions
and fish so can we assume they were
worshiping fish and tigers and lions
and birds
let's not make assumptions
now if you look at all the data
the archaeological data
the cultural data
the other data if we put it all together
it becomes obvious that there is only
one
identification we can make of the people
of the sindhu region from the harappan
phase of our civilization and that is
the vedic people now i cannot explain
all of that over here it takes hours i
have lots of videos about that you can
also look at the the conversation i had
with dr niraj in which we go into that
in detail so i cannot give an answer
about this and explain everything and
debunk everything in five minutes
it takes time there are so many layers
of evidence that you have to look into
so i have written articles about this i
have explained about this in great
detail in certain episodes i think i
have at least one episode ask a buddhist
which is dedicated only to the rn
invasion myth
and i have this conversation with dr
nirajaray so it will take if you want to
understand this in depth it's going to
take you some investment of time
i cannot give you all the evidence right
here right now in five minutes not
possible but i appreciate the question
it's a very good question many people
will have the question so what i would
suggest is look at
uh the other videos i have on the
channel look at my conversations
listen to the conversation with dr niraj
rai
watch my episode on the aryan invasion
theory
read up
i have a couple of articles just google
it right
and it's going to take some time for you
to understand all of this but
all the evidence all of the evidence
points to the fact that the
vedic phase of indian civilization and
the so-called harappan phase is one and
the same
so you will need to
invest the time
dedicate some time and learn this
examine all the evidence for yourself
and then use your own intelligence and
logic
to come to your own conclusions
but the conclusions i have come at after
studying this for so long
is that these two are one and the same
all right
okay is there anything else i can take
we are almost at two hours so
um
okay this is the last question for today
why does india not build a military like
russia like russia has a small economy
but a powerful military well please
understand sir pushkarji clash with
pushkar
russia is no longer in the top 10
economies yes
but do you remember how the world was 30
years ago
40 years ago russia was a military
economic and all-round superpower
and the military they built up at that
time it still exists so today's russia
even though it has a small economy has a
very powerful military because of what
it inherited from the ussr they have
continued that
and they also inherited this massive
nuclear arsenal from the ussr so that's
why despite being such a small economy
they have a massively powerful military
that's the reason
now india did not get any inheritance of
that kind
so we are building up everything the
military the navy everything as we go
today so as our economy expands and
grows larger our military capabilities
resolve will also be augmented
proportionally so that is the reason
why we witness this different trajectory
when it comes to india
all right
ladies and gentlemen
thank you so much for all the questions
very interesting session as always
tomorrow i'm gonna have another session
which is going to be a video chat
session
so
please come prepared with your best
questions and i will hopefully speak to
as many of you as possible face to face
on the screen until that time thank you
so much for your questions for your
viewership for your support i really
appreciate that very grateful and i'll
see you tomorrow thank you